<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ImplementationGuide
    xmlns="http://hl7.org/fhir">
    <id value="hl7-fhir-us-imp-med-admin"/>
    <meta>
        <versionId value="3"/>
        <lastUpdated value="2020-12-17T23:03:52.052+00:00"/>
        <source value="#MEtgcndwcv13UKdm"/>
    </meta>
    <url value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/ade-hypo/ImplementationGuide/hl7-fhir-us-imp-med-admin"/>
    <version value="0.1.0"/>
    <name value="InpatientMedicationAdministrationNHSN"/>
    <title value="NHSN Reporting: Inpatient Medication Administration"/>
    <status value="draft"/>
    <publisher value="HL7 International - Pharmacy Work Group"/>
    <contact>
        <name value="HL7 International - Pharmacy"/>
        <telecom>
            <system value="url"/>
            <value value="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/medication"/>
        </telecom>
    </contact>
    <description value="This IG will support electronic submission of line-level medication administration data to the National Healthcare Safety Network (NHSN). The intent of this project is to establish an electronic submission standard that is vendor-neutral that leverages existing workflows and eliminates duplicate documentation. This project will work with EHR vendors to identify data elements that can be used to describe medications administered (name, formulation, route, dose, duration) to hospitalized patients (inpatients) diagnosed with COVID-19 as part of NHSN COVID-19 reporting pathways. Medication administration events would be reported irrespective of whether or not medication administration was linked to an adverse event, refer to clinician-administered events (e.g., nurse giving a patient their medication dose), and only those occurring in inpatient settings; this excludes: emergency department, observation/short stay, inpatient rehabilitation, outpatient surgical centers, and other outpatient (including physician office) settings.&#xA;&#xA;Medication data are integral to informing the quality, safety, and costs of U.S. healthcare, supporting federal, state, and local public health, and guiding clinical decision-making in patient care. In inpatient workflows, medication administration—as captured by electronic medication administration (eMAR) records—is considered the gold standard for accurately measuring in-hospital medication exposure, including identifying the exact medications patients have received, in what formulations, doses, and for what duration of time. Published data indicate that alternate data sources for medication exposure, such as pharmacy &quot;order&quot; (or billing) data and medication &quot;lists&quot; are inaccurate representations of in-hospital medication exposure. Pharmacy order/billing data are discordant with medication administration data due to variability in when billing events occur relative to actual medication administration (1,2). For example, order/billing can occur upon order entry or upon dispensing, neither of which reflects actual medication administration to the patient. Despite an order/billing event, actual administration to the patient can be held, missed, or discontinued (prior to a discontinuation order reaching the pharmacy). Medication &quot;lists&quot;, such as those generated during medication reconciliation are based on processes that are highly variable across U.S hospitals with regard to their accuracy and comprehensiveness (3). Medication lists can also have a high level of discordance with actual administration of medications (4,5). The need for medication administration information has never been clearer as during the COVID-19 pandemic, where identification of the medications that acutely ill hospitalized patients with COVID-19 had received was integral to understanding clinical management of this new public health threat and directing public health resources, including scarce medications. The continued reliance on the &quot;medication list&quot; resource instead of the &quot;medication administration&quot; resource is a severe limitation in achieving accurate representation of medication exposure in U.S. healthcare data through FHIR resources. &#xA;  &#xA;1. Courter JD, Parker SK, Thurm C, Kronman MP, Weissman SJ, Shah SS, Hersh AL, Brogan TV, Patel SJ, Smith MJ, Lee BR, Newland JG, Gerber JS. Accuracy of administrative data for antimicrobial administration in hospitalized children. J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc 2018;7(3):261-63.  &#xA;2. Schwartz DN, Evans RS, Camins BC, Khan YN, Lloyd JF, Shehab N, Stevenson K. Deriving measures of intensive care unit antimicrobial use from computerized pharmacy data: methods, validation, and overcoming barriers. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 2011;32(5):472-80.   &#xA;3. Pevnick JM, Shane R, Schnipper JL. The problem with medication reconciliation. BMJ Qual Saf 2016; 25(9):726-30.&#xA;4. Rose AJ, Fisher SH, Passche-Orlow MK. Beyond medication reconciliation. The correct medication list. JAMA 2017;317(20):2057-8. &#xA;5. Gupta A, Yek C, Hendler RS. Phenytoin toxicity. JAMA 2017;317(23):2445-6.  "/>
    <jurisdiction>
        <coding>
            <system value="urn:iso:std:iso:3166:-2"/>
            <code value="US"/>
        </coding>
    </jurisdiction>
    <packageId value="hl7.fhir.us.imp-med-admin"/>
    <fhirVersion value="4.0.1"/>
    <dependsOn>
        <uri value="http://hl7.org/fhir/us/core/ImplementationGuide/hl7.fhir.us.core#3.1.1"/>
        <packageId value="hl7.fhir.us.core"/>
        <version value="3.1.1"/>
    </dependsOn>
    <definition>
        <resource>
            <reference>
                <reference value="StructureDefinition/Composition-inpatient-med-admin"/>
                <display value="Composition - Inpatient Medication Administration"/>
            </reference>
            <name value="Composition - Inpatient Medication Administration"/>
            <description value="This profile supports the electronic submission of line-level medication administration data to the National Healthcare Safety Network (NHSN)."/>
            <exampleBoolean value="false"/>
        </resource>
        <page>
            <nameUrl value="index.html"/>
            <title value="Home Page"/>
            <generation value="markdown"/>
        </page>
        <parameter>
            <code value="copyrightyear"/>
            <value value="2020+"/>
        </parameter>
        <parameter>
            <code value="releaselabel"/>
            <value value="CI Build"/>
        </parameter>
    </definition>
</ImplementationGuide>